welcome to this intro to machine
learning course from Rola Dolly Rola is
an AI engineer and has a PHD in
Neuroscience the course starts with the
fundamentals covering what machine
learning is how it differs from
traditional approaches and when it's
used it then Dives deeper into the
mechanics exploring different models
algorithms and training processes next
it covers generative AI before wrapping
up with the architecture of AI systems
and how to design deploy them
effectively hello everyone my name is uh
Rola D I am a machine learning architect
and uh what I want to do here today is
to give you some background information
on machine learning so this is really a
primer for people without um ml
knowledge it's not supposed to go into
technical great technical detail I just
want to give you practically the lay of
the land um and so I'll take you through
this so um just a little bit about
myself again I'm a machine learning
architect at rapid scale um we serve the
US market and I help customers build
machine Learning Systems every day um I
come from an academic background so I
have a PhD in N science and biomatics I
graduated from Mill University in
2017 um I like to say that I was
interested in human intelligence and now
I work more in artificial intelligence I
really like like to compare and contrast
um the two
occasionally um I'm also an AWS
Enthusiast so I'm an AWS Community
Builder I'm the AWS Montreal uh co-lead
and I'm also a an an AWS Ambassador for
Rapid scale I'm a gold jacket Ambassador
which means that I have completed all 12
certifications um on a personal side I
am a mother of two little angels that
keep me busy and I love to cake um
although I don't get to do that as much
anymore um so in terms of what I've got
here today it's a series uh a four part
series um I'm going to go through what
I'm calling ml11 which is an
introduction to machine learning ml12
which is really ml under the hood so
we'll talk a little bit about algorithms
just to peel a layer off and and give
you a better understanding of what is
going on ml13 is an introduction to
generative AI
and 104 is about architecting a gen
system okay so they shouldn't be um long
I'm expecting about 30 minutes a lecture
hopefully I do tend to go off rails
sometimes so let's say 45 minutes and um
hopefully it's useful so I'll see you in
the next one hello again um so let's
start with ml11 so this is an
introduction to machine learning again
it assumes no knowledge um and this is
supposed to be for a beginner
audience so um I'll go through what
machine learning is in terms of
definition how it's different from
computer science how it's different from
statistics where to use it and where not
to use it and a little bit about the
machine learning life cycle talk a
little bit about ML on AWS um it looks
um it's fairly similar to how it look it
works on cloud in general but I am um an
AWS prati heavy practitioner so I'll
choose AWS and then I'll look at um
artificial intelligence versus human
intelligence again in Ode to my
doctorate studies okay so what is
machine learning so in terms of
definition and if you looked if you
asked Google um then you'll get a uh a
definition from Oxford languages which
says machine learning is the use and
development of computer systems that are
able to learn and adapt without
following explicit instruction
and by using algorithms and statistical
models to analyze and draw inferences
from patterns in the data I don't know
if you understood anything from that but
it's pretty uh long so let's deconstruct
this a little bit so machine learning
systems are computer systems um they are
based on algorithm and statistical
models and they learn patterns in the
data without following explicit
instructions so these are the four core
things I think in here and so if I were
to rewrite this I would say that machine
learning is really powerful mathematics
powered by computer systems that learn
patterns in the data without explicitly
being taught that's my
definition and that that's exactly what
it is so it's it's math it's computers
it's
data and so how is it different from
computer software so ml has been called
software
2.0 uh so how is it really different
from so uh traditional software well
there's two steps to any software system
there's there's the development step and
then there's the deployment step right
so in traditional software during
development you've got yourself a
computer and what you do is you sit down
and you write your code this is the
formula you sit down and whatever
language you choose you you write a set
of statements right if this happens do
that when this happens do this other
thing and so on so that's your code and
then what happens is you give the code
an input the computer crunches all of
this and gives you an output right now
how is that different in machine
learning well in machine learning
development this is what we call
training and you've got a
computer but then instead of actually
writing the formula what you do is you
give it the
input and you give it the output this is
a specific type called supervised
learning but it it's it's one of the
more popular types so that's what I'm
going to use and so you've got yourself
a computer you give it the input and you
give it the output it crunches the
information and it tells you the formula
so this is really interesting in places
where we don't know the formula
ourselves we don't think there's
complexity um or or there's things that
we just don't understand right so this
is how it works that's the main
difference is that in a traditional
computer system you write the formula
and in a machine Learning System the
formula is the actual output during
training um the formula there's a lot of
other terminology the formula is a
pattern it's an algorithm it's a recipe
um instructions in machine learning it's
the actual model the term is the
model now when it comes to deployment
what ends up happening is you deploy
this this software system on a computer
your user inputs the puts the input in
and gets an output now in machine
learning deployment this is what we call
in difference or prediction again you
deploy this formula now that that that
you got out of training you deploy that
and you get an output so at deployment
time um software and and machine
Learning Systems look fairly
similar uh but the difference mainly is
at training
time so how is it different from
statistics there's a lot of people tend
to confuse statistics and ml sometimes
so let me tell you a little bit about uh
the different types of analytics um we
distinguish four types of analytics so
there's descriptive analytics which
explains what
happened um there's diagnostic analytics
which explains why it actually happened
there's Predictive Analytics which
describe which forecast what might
happen in the future and prescriptive
analytics which recommends action based
on that predicted forecast and as you
move through this to the right um
there's there's more insight and
foresight and
so
statistics really is at the different
scale than machine learning is machine
learning really um excels at prediction
um and and
foresight and
so both statistics and machine learning
are both part of the data set uh toolkit
they both aim at defining mathematical
representations of the real world uh
which we call a model and um but
statistics is more concerned with
understanding population descriptions
what is your mean what is your your
variance uh what is your sample size how
does the sample represent the bigger
population things like that uh whereas
ml is more concerned with predicting
unseen data so more projecting based on
the information I have today can I
project later and so the machine
learning superpow is really prediction
it's using information you have you have
to to predict information you do not
have and the importance of that is
really reducing uncertainty and being
more prepared and so as humans I think
we we have always had a fascination with
prediction so I took Greek mythology and
my in my undergrad and this is the
Oracle of Deli which was one of the most
famous Greek uh oracles and people would
go in for predictions and there's a lot
of stories of war in the ancient world
that that were based on different
predictions and I mean uh for tellers
are forms of predictors although they
they're a different backend um than ml
but there is a Fascination there's a
human fascination with
prediction and so um I'll take you
through some ml terminology um
artificial intelligence or AI in the
field um is defined as techniques that
enable computers to mimic human behavior
so these are things like robots these
are things um that just allow systems to
behave humanlike right so what is
machine learning or ml these are AI
techniques that allow computers to learn
without explicit programming so these
are specifically mimicking the learning
capability of of humans and so you've
got artificial intelligence which is the
bigger uh bucket and machine learning is
a subset of that so what is artificial
intelligence that is not machine
learning well there's things like
robotics because robots mimic human uh
motion uh and other aspects but they are
uh code based or they're programmed
specifically to do that um there's NLP
syntax and semantics so NLP can be if
it's based on
um uh learning uh then it could be part
of machine learning but there's a whole
part of NLP that is really rule-based
that is outside of uh machine
learning deep learning is a subset of
machine learning which uses multi-layer
neuron metric is inspired by the human
brain um and so again that's a subset of
ml other algorithms that are not in this
are for example svms logistic regression
linear regression XG boost there's a
whole lot of um different types of
algorithms and we'll go through that in
the second
lecture generative AI is a type of AI
that allows computers to generate new
content and we'll see again across the
series what that really means
means um so the rise of ml I find this
really interesting and and I I wanted to
mention it so um the AI has been is a
field that has been around for a really
long time um these are the AI Godfathers
what are known as the AI Godfathers
there's uh Jeffrey Hinton yan yan Lon
and yosua Benjo and they did their phds
in the 70s and and 80s and 90s on uh
machine learning they they um
they have done a lot of work on uh the
the Deep learning and and a lot of
really uh cool techniques they've really
revived the field that that's why
they're called the AI uh Godfathers but
the first papers the first academic
papers on machine learning are as old as
1940s right and so we've why did it take
so long why has it been 80 years um that
right now is super popular and there's a
number of reasons so there's an increase
in number of devices in data in in um
just information uh there's an increase
in computer speed in memory so now we
have data we can process that data and
there is an explosion of algorithms and
mathematical
models and there's increased demand for
customized Solutions and Data drien
Systems I think there's a realization of
the potential power in data M ML and so
if we look at this um the ml
foundational pillars based on the
definition I Told You So machine
learning systems are really based on um
data mathematical algorithms and uh
computer systems and there has been a
huge con a huge conversion and and an
explosion of information across all
these fields and and one of my my um one
of the resources I really like is this
McKenzie
um uh diagram let me show it to you it's
really cool um so if you look at yai and
then they show you um some of the things
that happen in the exposion of data so
the N the opening of the internet in
1991 has really um just exploded the
amount of data that we have we bring
tracked um across everything we do and
so you can see here across all of the
things that have happened and it's
really interesting to to see that and
I've I've played with this several times
there's algorithmic advancements again
you can see all of the things that some
of the really major uh things that have
um changed the field and then you've got
increases in
power and they all converge to here to
2009 um with Andrew using gpus to train
deep learning models and so on and you
can look at this this is one of I really
like this
resource and so um yeah we're at an era
where computers cheap there's a lot of
smart people creating a lot of really
cool algorithms and there's a lot of
data so it's it's really um great uh for
machine
learning okay so when is MLA fit for
your use case and what are some anti
patterns um anytime there is data
machine learning is a possible option
right because it can learn patterns in
the data it is a great fit though I tell
my clients it's a it's an actually great
fit a no-brainer when there's scales
scale so if you because machines scale
much much better than humans so if you
have an operation you have you're
running a company and you want to double
your operations if you have um a system
that is not based on machine learning
for example you would have to hire
double the people uh by double the death
by by double the resources the space
train um and so on whereas if this was a
machine Learning System uh let's say on
in the cloud then with a few clicks you
could potentially double or triple or so
on you could scale really well really
fast so when there's scale machine
learning is is uh is a great option when
there's change
because um we're now living in a global
world it's an interconnected world and
things change very fast and for us to um
detect change and then uh try to
understand it try to model it try to
make um predictions out of it manually
or or it's going to
be things move so fast that we can't do
that cycle efficiently but if we have an
an mlof system uh then it can detect a
change and and Trigger um uh training
and and and deployment and so on so
again with change um ML and mlops are a
better uh solution than other options
and in terms of complexity because when
patterns are too complex to tease out uh
machine learning shines in complexity
and so when is it a great fit scale
change and
complexity when is it an anti pattern
well um I used to say when you don't
have enough data or bad quality data
that is of course making the assumption
that you want to train your own models
today there's a lot of pre-trained
models so you don't have to do that so
if you do want to train your own model
then data is definitely a prerequisite
uh but you can use pre-trained models if
if simpler Solutions exist and do the
trick really well then you don't really
need machine learning um there is a an
onboarding cost right there there is a
skill set required there is a setup
required and so on so um if your systems
work and they're fine maybe you don't
need it and if it's not a cost-
effective right um if you if you're
using a system it should be cost-
effective and there's a word of caution
I wanted to say um in previous in the
previous decade there was a lot of
disappointment in machine learning uh
because there I think there was a huge
disconnect between the engineers on the
ground that were uh optimizing for
technical objectives and the business
itself self which was looking at
business goals and there was a there's a
disconnect between um the actual
technical objectives and the business
needs uh because the engineers would
optimize the objective function the
model would work but it wouldn't be tied
to the business and not created a bit of
frustration and so if you are an ml
engineer um ml serves the business so
you need to connect you need to model
your problem to serve the business and
we'll talk a little bit more about that
in in the life
cycle um so this one this is about the
automation life cycle so machine uh
learning machine human interaction
skills people assume that people are are
sometimes scared uh about ml it doesn't
have to be an all or none
situation um there's different
configurations that you can set up in
your company so on one scale you've got
the human only system so these are
humans these are systems run fully by
humans um on the very other end of the
scale you've got systems that are fully
run by machines right so there's full
automation um and there's very very few
systems I think in the world that do
this very few companies uh that do this
it's certainly not everybody uh although
they you know we we um we try to set
these system up but um again you don't
have
to um in the middle there's a whole
spectrum of things so there's Shadow
mode where the machine learning Shadows
the human uh but its output is not used
this could be done for compliance this
could be done for training this can be
done for different reasons for
understanding systems um then you've got
AI assistance where the human is the
primary driver and then there's a uh
machine Learning System that the human
can tap into as required so these are
people in call centers for example have
an auxiliary system that helps them do
their job fast and um different
positions where we put an auxiliary
system that helps the person but you're
still interacting with a human
first and then we've got partial
automation where um the machine learning
does the actual work um it is in the
Forefront but then there's human gating
and validation and approval so uh
there's some sort of control by humans
and ml is an inter iterative and
experimental process towards maturity so
you start early and you keep iterating
towards the system that you are
comfortable with and I always tell
clients that you know if you wait for
technology to prove its worth for the
rest of the industry before you jump in
then you might be playing catchup for a
really long time right so um stay up to
date with new technology try to to
dabble into it and and just to at least
be aware of what's going on in the
field okay so the machine learning life
cycle um this is my five petal flower
that I've Illustrated uh so always we
start with the business again Tech
serves the business we start from
business needs we identify the goals we
frame the problem we choose the metrics
and plan the process we come into the
data so we collect we explore we
transform then we go into the model
domain we choose our model we train it
we evaluate it we optimize it and then
we deploy it and then uh we mon we uh
maintain it and monitor it and so so um
some interesting um steps there so the
most important one I think uh is really
defining and framing the problem and so
what this means is that again the
business has a goal a business goal and
there's a million ways that that
business goal can be transposed into
mathematical space right what is the
proxy um what me metrics proxy that
business goal what does it mean in
mathematical representation so that's
called framing the problem and and
that's probably one of the most
important steps I would say uh when
you're an ml engineer is to really
understand the business goal and
formulate it in mathematical
terms then there's the data preparation
phase the model phase the deployment and
the
operations so
um I I'm a great fan of AWS but again
this works um pretty similarly in most
clubs what I want to show you is that
these clouds um they provide services to
different personas this is a fairly old
uh representation so all of the a lot of
the services they have a lot more
services now uh but I just want to show
you the
layering and so at the bottom oops
oops at the bottom here um we've got
Frameworks uh these are chips these are
uh base libraries that people can use um
so this these are systems that an ml
engineer would use to build from scratch
but not everybody would need that um
above that they have a layer which is a
little bit more abstracted so um this is
these say J maker for example has um a
lot of abstracted capabilities for you
this is for example where a data
scientist uh might Thrive above that
they have a a layer of uh pre-trained
models so ml as a
as a service and um this is for
everybody it's an API call that you can
make and these are models that uh the
provide the AWS for
example
maintains and so as you go up the scale
there's an abstraction uh so there's
ease of use but then as you go down
there's a lot more control and so if uh
you're interested in machine learning
wherever you are in that Spectrum there
is a tool for you um and so you just
need to just identify where you are here
and and look um
there this is true for generative AI as
well it's the same stack so at the
bottom you've got your infrastructure on
the top you've got your platforms and
then uh on the very top you've got your
uh SAS
models and uh this is my last slide so
this is the brains versus Bots uh this
is an article that I had wrote
previously about comparing hum and uh
artificial
intelligence um
so they're both predictive machines
right so I told you through this
presentation that uh machine learning is
uh the the main power is predictive
power um it's interesting that brains
are also predictive I think that caught
neuroscientist by surprise
um there's a lot of evidence today that
the brain predicts
uh actions before they happen so when
you drink water for example uh you get
uh satiated before the water hits your
stomach right or or travels through your
system and and that's a prediction from
your brain that your system is going to
go through homeostasis right so there's
a predictive capability um and and that
makes sense right and and there's a lot
of examples about this and it makes
sense because an ancestor who would have
waited to react would have been eaten um
and not survived and so
um it's interesting I I I when I learned
this it was um I was a little surprised
I must say but there's a lot of um
evidence today to support
this in terms of counts or or size um of
course uh brains uh the main processing
unit of the brain is the neuron um we
can look at synapses which is which are
the neuron neuron to neuron connection
um and there's about 100 trillion sign
in the brain the equivalent to that in
the Bots are parameters or weights um
and today there's about two trillion in
the state of the-art models roughly
about 1.8 but I'm I'm averaging to to
roughly two
trillions and so brains are still about
50 times more
interconnected
um than any of our models and the brain
is still a lot better at integrating
data
holistically um we have been evolving
for about 300,000 years and so we um
handle information still a lot better
than models do so in terms of winner the
brain is the winner
here in terms of training time again uh
the brain has been evolving for 300,000
years um and your own um well there's
typo here but your own instance has been
fine-tuning for the L length of your own
age right um Bots however are a lot
younger so I just told you the field is
about 80 years old and in started in
1940s so let's say about 100 but it is a
product of human Ingenuity right um
there's a lot of
effort that um is being dumped
into uh artificial intelligence there's
a lot of money going there there's a lot
of interest and so um um so the Bots
have had a lot less time in terms of
training time machines have a way to go
still to um catch up with the brain so
the brain wins but not I assume in
another few decades this would not be
the
case um speed again brains uh depend on
neurotransmitters diffusing through
liquids so these are
the neurotransmitters that are used to
communicate and that's estimated at
about let's say 200 Herz um Bots depend
on electrons running through transistors
and today CPU clock rate is about is
over 10 gahz right so Bots are about 50
times faster than brains are or could
ever
be in terms of input modalities um we
are Tethered to biology our brain gets
um input input through our five senses
uh whereas
Bots have unlimited input streams so if
you've ever built an Arduino um or or
you know any particular system you can
buy tons and tons of different um iot
devices and input devices that you can
add through the systems and you can
figure out how to process that data so
Bots have unlimited in input streams
which we cannot
match and so machine Learning Systems
have huge potential uh because of their
speed
and augmentation capability so the fact
that we are Tethered to biology kind of
um gives us the short end of the stick
here uh so there I it is no surprise
that AI will be the Workhorse of the
future so I suggest everybody learns
ML and these are some of the resources
um that I've used along my way getting
into the field I've been in the field
since 2012 uh so I put them here I'm
really ing uh these notes as well so you
could be able to click through these and
that's it so this is ml12 so this is
machine learning under the hood so what
we're going to do is we're going to
delve a little bit further into models
and so on um again not too deep or not
too technical but a lot of people say
well what's happening um a little deeper
and so I'm going to take you one
level uh down and so um I'm going to
start with the types of machine learning
so there's different types or categories
of machine learning and um right now the
the the major classification is four
different types so there's supervised
learning this is when the model
learns um from data with labels so we
already know what the right solution is
and the model tends to mimic that
unsupervised learning is when the model
learns from data without labels so we do
not know what the right answer is and
then the model tries to make some sense
or some pattern in the
data reinforcement learning is um a type
of machine learning which um solves
multi-step problems uh by maximizing a
reward function and generative AI um are
models that generate new content and if
you read a machine learning book before
November
2022 um you wouldn't have seen the
fourth type so before November 2022 most
books would have told you there's three
types of machine learning supervised on
supervis and reinforcement learning in
November 2022 open AI released chbt to
the public and of course it caught fire
and since then um I think everything we
can hear of of is J ji so again if
you're reading older res sources you
would not see that now um
what the the the terminology that I'm
going to use um for the three um classes
of ml uh that are not gen is predictive
ml or classical ml some people call it
traditional ml or um and then gen so I'm
going to call them predictive ML and
gen and you have to remember that um AI
or ml are is really a set of tools it's
a toolkit
that um solves problems it it's a
general purpose technology Andrew Ang um
always says it it's it's electricity
right it's the new age
electricity
um and it is what it is really is um
mapping input to
Output um and the last decade was a lot
about optimizing supervised learning so
if you were you if you've been in the
field for really long time like I have
it was really a lot about supervised
learning we had a deep learning boom a
decade ago um and now it's all about gen
so the prediction is that this decade is
more about gen and um one interesting
thing that I wanted to mention is that
um if a model is small and we we'll see
what that means what does it mean for a
model that is small but let's say if a
model is
small what increasing amount of the data
will eventually Plateau performance
because we say the model overfits which
means it memorizes the data what we're
saying and this was true for supervised
learning we were that was something we
really watched out for that is not true
for generative AI we're not seeing
overfitting for generative AI yet and so
the more data we give it the better
performance so there's a huge difference
in performance between um supervised
learning uh and generative AI in that uh
we are not seeing overfitting yet and
and that's partly because these models
are are huge and so the amount of data
that it would take them to overfit is
probably quite usual we're not there
yet okay so let's let's take a step back
what is a model and um and so again like
I told you uh before a model is a
mathematical representation of a real
world system right uh it's a model it's
an algorithm it's a formula it's a
pattern um mathematically it's an
equation um and the way I think of them
is machine learning models are really
big statistical calculators right is
just playing with numbers uh and tuning
them the right
way model components um there are these
are what we mathematically represent
things again we're not going to go into
too too much technical detail but um
it's just good to to know some of these
things so the Y is um the class to be
predicted this is what we're trying to
predict it will be the model output what
we call X is the input data so these are
also called the features so this is the
information that uh the model will take
in to predict the model output the
parameters or the weights um are tunable
numbers in the model that encode the
learning so uh we'll see some
formulas and of course uh what really
matters as well is the model
architecture class so this is the actual
formula or equation and we'll we'll see
a couple and so the model class uh
defines the mathematical formula use so
for example a linear regression uh class
uses a formula in the shape of yal ax
plus b where Y is of course the the
output class this is what we're trying
to predict X is the input features this
is what we are what the the information
we have and a and b are the parameters
so these are the weights and what will
happen we'll see an example of this what
will happen is that the model will try
to find the right values of A and B
where if given X it can predict y right
and this in in this way the way I've
written it here it looks like this is a
single column and it it could be uh but
in reality this is a this is a series of
columns so this this would be a
vector and so it would be y equals if I
would expand it out it would be yal A1
X1 plus A2 X2 plus so on a A anxn plus b
okay um another example so if logistic
regression for example this this um ends
up this is used when y um is continuous
a logistic regression is used when Y is
discrete um and again if you don't know
what these are don't don't worry about
it um I'm just trying to show you a
little bit under the hood it's not
necessary for the rest of the exercises
but um just in case you are interested
so a logistic regression is you take the
linear regression model and you you pass
it through a sigo function which is an
activation function again if you don't
know what that is you don't really need
to but the idea is to show you that
underneath these systems is an actual
mathematical equation right and this is
the simplest one so I put these here
because they are the simplest ones but
as models become too big the exact
mathematical equation becomes too
complex and so we visualize their
architecture with abstract diagrams okay
and we'll see a couple of these but at
again at the heart of it is a
mathematical
equation and so these are some of the
types of algorithms we've got linear
regression logistic regression decision
trees random Forest naive Bays um
support Vector machines svms neural Nets
um these blue ones are for unsupervised
learning so nearest neighbor uh
clustering and and some dimensionality
reduction again um this is a lot of what
what predictive ml was um concerned with
is choosing the right class of model
understanding what these models do what
is the equation underlying them where
does it Excel when do I use it how do I
optimize it this is not so much this is
not true of course for Gen but um I'm
just want wanted to show you if we peel
one layer up so we're not going to go
into these um I just I'm using them as
an example to explain to you what
parameters are hyper parameters and so
on I do want to go a little bit into
deep learning or neuron lets because
they are the underlying foundation for a
lot of things including CH so deep
learning um the human brain is made of
different
layers six layers to be exact of neurons
that are stacked um and the way the
human brain works is that neurons
interconnect with each other um and
there's a lot of there's thousands and
thousands of connections per
neuron and this is a um an image from
Ramon kahal the neuro the the father of
Neuroscience um and you can see the
layer of neurons so this is a layer and
this is a layer and how they
interconnect and so um neural Nets
artificial neural networks what they try
to do is mimic that behavior and so what
you've got here is um a neuron this is a
processing unit this is a at its heart
is a logistic regression function and we
stack them so there's a layer here this
is the input layer and then we've got
another layer so you think of them as
you've got layers and layers and layers
and this is it you've got layers and
layers and layers and this is the first
one is called the input layer the last
one is called the output layer and
everything in between is called a hidden
layer and um what these are the
connections here but from neuron to
neuron um are the parameters are so this
is the strength of connection the
parameters what they do is um they
encode the strength of connections again
you don't need to know that but um we're
going to
see so again I didn't uh put the formula
here because this would be quite complex
these would be logistic regression so
these would be
um and then they would connect to each
of these each of them would connect to
each of them and um when I was in
graduate school we did actually write
those and we coded them up in Python and
so on but uh we do not need to do that
here but um you're going to see another
so these are the underlying systems
again um that in Co Transformers and ji
but um we don't really need to get any
deeper than
that so what is a parameter uh and what
is a hyperparameter so a parameter a
model parameter is a tunable variable so
this is something that um the model can
change and it is in internal to the
model and whose value can be learned
from the data through training okay and
this is what encodes the learning of the
model so two different models that have
seen different data would have different
parameter values or different weights
parameters and weights are the same um
refer to the same thing what are model
hyper parameters well these are
variables that are external to the model
um their value cannot be learned from
the data but what hyper parameters do um
is that they control the learning
process and so examples of
hyperparameters of their learning rate
of certain uh algorithms the number of
epoch this is how many training Cycles
the system went through regularization
this is um a system that con constrains
the the model from getting to Big um so
when you download a Model A pre-trained
model what you're actually downloading
are the parameters of the weights of
that model you are not um I don't know
that hyper parameters are always
included they don't affect
the um model performance uh but so
models are sized by the number of
parameters and hyperparameters are good
to keep track of because they might
explain they might allow you to
troubleshoot through things but they're
not um they don't they are not important
for the actual um learned information
they're important for the learning
process
okay okay so solving a
um supervised learning problem uh we
went through this in um
the the previous um session so I'm just
going to go through it very quickly uh
and so again we start with the business
um Tech serves the business and so we
always start with the business we
understand the business goal um we try
to frame the problem which means we
transform that um business problem into
uh mathematical
um notations uh we understand what
metrics are great proxies we we plan the
process then once we do that uh we go
into the data realm we collect data we
clean it up we decide on what our
features are what
matters um and then we get into the
model domain so we select a model class
we decide is this a classification is it
a regression uh what model fits best uh
you know am I running a neural net am I
running running in svm I don't think
anybody runs svms anymore but um they
were very popular before the Deep
learning boom am I running an XG boost a
random
Forest uh and so you set that model you
train it you evaluate it you optimize it
and then once you're happy with its
performance uh and it generalizes it's
very important that you're that it
generalizes well um then you deploy it
and you'll maintain it
okay and so what does training a
supervis model look like well what
happens is that again it has the the the
learning itself is encoded in these
weights or parameters what ends up
happening is that the model when you
start training it initializes them at
random so um it starts them at random it
makes a prediction so it says okay well
this is in supervised learning so I know
the answer uh we we know the answer to
to to these um uh instances we're
looking at and so it makes a prediction
and then it looks how far is it from the
actual data it calculates some sort of
metric it could be we call it an error
but it could be um in reality it's
optimizing an objective function so that
could be it could be maximizing accuracy
for example or minimizing error so that
the general term is optimizing objective
function but I'm making the Assumption
here that I'm I'm minimizing an error
and so I can calculate the error between
the model predictions and the answers
and then it goes in and edits the weight
the weights to reduce that error um and
then it tries again and so what it does
is it repeats the Cycles two to four
until the error doesn't go down and I'll
give you and I'll show you an example of
how this is done in one of the demos so
you adjust you start the models you
predict you calculate an error then you
adjust the models and you keep doing
this until you can no longer reduce the
error okay and so I have two I have
three demos here I'm going to put them
in separate uh videos uh and so I'm
going to demo how
software is different from machine
Learning Systems um I have a little bit
a little notebook which I'll release uh
to you for you to play with um I'll also
demo um this training uh how how that
works with the uh linear regression
which is a very simple model and I also
want to demo the tensor F uh playground
which I like very much so I'm going to
releasee those as separate videos and
that's it for this one hello again so
this is the demo um that is with the
ml11 lecture so what I'm going to demo
here is the software versus ml approach
to solving problems um and then I'm
going to demo uh the model training
visualization okay so um let me go here
and so what this is this is a notebook a
Jupiter notebook that I will again uh
release uh for you to play with and
um and what I'm showing here is how we
would solve this
um uh Celsius conversion from Fahrenheit
or Fahrenheit conversion uh from Celsius
uh using uh software versus ml okay so
uh in for traditional software we do
know the formula that
um encodes Fahrenheit to Celsius uh
conversion and that's the the
temperature in Fahrenheit is equal to
1.8 time the temperature in celsius plus
32 so now given that I know this I can
write a function that goes in and uh
given an input in Celsius goes in and
returns a
Farenheit uh temperature and so this is
my formula or my code um again this is a
single function it's simple for for for
demonstration purposes but you can
imagine that this is a larger piece of
code and then I am going to deploy it
which is here just asking for user input
but you can again imagine that this is a
more complex system and so if I am to
run that it's going to tell me Well
enter your temperature in celsius I'm
going to enter minus
27 which is the temperature here today
in
Montreal and that's going to tell me
that it's- 16.6 fah okay so again I
wrote my formula which I already know my
I wrote my rules I know the rule I wrote
it up uh you deploy it and then you you
uh allow your users to interact with it
and then you maintain it now what
happens in a machine Learning System
well in a machine Learning System um
what usually happens is you do not know
this formula okay what you have is data
and so let's say I work for a company
and that company has both uh Celsius
thermometers and Fahrenheit thermometers
in the field that are collecting data
all the time and what ends up happening
uh is that the fahrenheit thermometers
they break they broke and uh it's too
costly to fix and there's a shortage so
we need that data we need that
information but I don't have a way to
collect it directly but my Celsius uh
sensors are still um picking up signal
and so what I want to do is to try to
predict uh the temperature in Fahrenheit
for my Downstream systems from the
sensors um in Celsius okay and so I'm
going to download my
data
and I want to show you what this looks
like so this is a set of data this is a
single file temperature. CSV which again
you're going to have access to um
there's two columns here this is degre
the the data in Celsius and this is the
data in Fahrenheit and if you go down
there's about 300 different uh rows in
this okay so this is the data that we
are
using and so here I'm going to download
this data and again it shows what I
showed you right there's a the First
Column is temperature in celsius the
second one is in Fahrenheit I've got 300
different rows and um there's some
statistical um metrics here uh and my
Min it goes all the way from -43 celsi
to 120 okay and this is data of course
that I generated myself with the formula
plus or minus uh 30 uh degrees of noise
so you're going to see that there's we
I've added some noise into there okay so
if we plot this uh this is what it looks
like so there's a temperature in
fahrenheit um and a temperature in
celsius and you can see that
uh that's the little noise I've added
now um it's easy to look at this because
um it's it's two columns So and I've
designed it that way for the reason
because it's easier to see things uh in
the real world you'll
never there's very few applications for
this for a single column and so uh
there's a lot of comp there's a lot more
columns and features in the real world
and visualization becomes a lot harder
but again I'm putting I'm making it
two-dimensional for you to to see the
difference
okay so now I've got this information
this is my my information prior to the
sensors breaking down so I do have some
information and now what I do have is my
um Celsius sensors are still picking up
data um and I don't have any Fahrenheit
anymore and what I'm trying to do is
take this information and predict my
Fahrenheit for Downstream systems okay
so how am I going to go about this well
um I'm going to import numpy um and a
ske learn uh psychic learn is um a
really good uh it's a found it's a
fundamental library in machine learning
what I'm importing here is linear
regression which is the model
class
um uh and this is this is for evaluation
and this is for spling the data we'll
see in uh the the code later what I'm
what I'm doing is I'm pulling my X which
is the Celsius column this is my input
or my feat
and I'm pulling my Y which is the actual
column that I want to predict this is my
output and then I choose a model class
um this is a linear regression because
the output um is continuous but also
because I mean I can see it's a line but
usually um there's a lot of work in
predictive ml in understanding what
these models what these model classes
are what is the underlying equation what
inputs do they take what outputs how
well do they do what space of
mathematics
um are they really good at and so on so
there's a lot of work in predictive ml
in terms of knowing your algorithms and
which one to use that's not true for
Gen but um okay so for this one I'm
going to use linear regression and so
this I've initiated a model that is a
linear regression model um I'm taking my
data I'm splitting at 3070 so 70 will go
to training and 30 would go for testing
the reason we do this is we want the
model to uh learn a pattern that can
generalize beyond the data that the
model sees if the model does really well
on the training data and does terribly
on the test data then it what we say
it's it it overfit which means it really
memorized the information which is not
what we want it to do we want the model
to generaliz on uh the test data so we
pull out um here 30% of the data that
the model will never see and once it
Tunes its
parameters
um on the training data then we'll use
that test data to evaluate whether it
generalized as well and here we're
training so SK learn is really nice and
that you can use model.fit
to um predict and then model uh to to to
train and then model. predict to uh
predict and so we're training here and
then we score the model by by taking the
r squ uh
coefficient and then we look at some
metrics so let me do this okay
so this model after training and again
we'll look at a linear regression
training in in the second notebook but
after training this model uh did uh 96 R
SAR these are I'm parting R squ yeah so
this is um 96 r squar on the training
and 95 on 95.9 on the test the fact that
these two numbers are really close tells
me that it's not overfitting that the
the the um performance on the test set
is s similar to that on the training set
and so the model is generalizing okay so
now I'm going to look at this model I'm
printing the coefficient um of
determination which is the r squ which
we've printed out here but also the
intercept and the slope so again a
linear regression is um in the formula
of yal ax plus b uh B is the intercept
and a is the slope so these are the two
parameters that the model has learned
and I'm printing them out and so when I
print them out this is what it looks
like and so when I run this so this the
M system after training thinks that the
temperature in Celsius is 1.8 times the
temperature in celsius plus 32 so this
is fairly close to the actual um formula
that we know is true again this depends
on how good your data is how much noise
is injected why did it know it exactly
because I injected noise um and it
didn't train that long there's only 300
um so the more data you have the cleaner
your data is then the more accurate your
your predict your model
is okay and so now that I've got this
formula I've trained I've got this
formula then I go in and deploy this
model so I'm using the model. predict uh
to to to get a prediction from this
model and so let me pull that out it's
going to tell me what did you do and I
think I use minus
27 and again this tells me based on the
software system that I I WR wrote above
it's minus 16.6 Fahrenheit and then on
the based on the ml uh prediction it's
1651 which is very very close right and
so this is the um that's how these two
things works if you know the rule if you
know the formula you type it up and if
you don't and you have data then you can
infer that formula from the data okay so
again I'm going to uh release this for
you to play with now the other
um model
I want to just see if all of these are
installed this is another computer so I
just want to make sure okay so uh what
this is again is a linear regression
model what we trained in the the the the
first notebook is a linear regression
model the linear regression model
equation of course is the y equal uh ax
plus b or WX plus b no matter how you
want to call it what the objective
function that um this model optimizes is
a is a Le square and this is equation
and no this is the error that it it uh
it
calculates and so it's minimizing this
subjective function anyway that's not
that not information you need but anyway
this is what's happening under the hood
so I've got some functions here that um
train this model and we're not going to
go into it in details but like I said in
the lecture um the model initially
initializes the weights at random so
this is the initialization code this is
the it calculates an error so this is
the cost function it's uh it's
calculating uh it predicts right because
it has to predict then use that
prediction to calculate an error and
then it updates the parameters so these
are the three things that we've seen in
that Loop and um uh it runs gradient
descent but that's
um okay and then I collect the cost
history and so on okay so there's some
functions here that are useful again I'm
downloading the same file the
temperature. CSV file which we just
looked at I'm going to load it
up and then again it's the same one so
we've got 300 going from -43 uh Celsius
to 120 okay so these are hyperparameters
so if I go back to this model
here if I go back to this model here
[Music]
um where is the temperature in the
temperature in Fahrenheit is what I want
to predict that's my y the temperature
in Celsius is my information that's
given that's my X that's my input data
um the two numbers that I
actually trained that that were tuned in
this model are this intercept and the
slope which is uh if we
go back um is really we found what this
1.8 and 32 are so if I go back here
actually it's this number here the W and
the B so these are my parameters okay my
weights my hyper parameters are going to
be um here for logistic for linear
regression uh is the linear the learning
rate which I've set at at this and and
the iterations these are the number of
epochs this is how many runs it's going
to do of this cycle of um
calculate uh
predict predict calculate error update
Waits this uh three system it's going to
do 10 Loops of that that's the epoch or
the iterations okay and so now I'm
running the gradient descent so I am
running this
model and then I'm going to print the
history so what I'm showing you here
this is iteration number one it's going
to do do through 10 so when it started
what we we looked at this so these are
my actual data this is my actual data
that I showed you before and this is the
model prediction okay so it initializes
the models at random and then it makes a
prediction and this is its prediction
and so it calculates a cost and the cost
here is 44
45.3 right there's no units for this
it's just a number but we have to
because uh this is an error we have to
bring it down and so what does it do
well it goes into iteration two so it
updates its weights so now it predicts
that this is a better prediction it
updates the weights creates a cost now
it's 2028
and then it goes again goes through
another cycle and so now it has this
guess with this cost this guess what
this cost this guess what this cost and
by the end of it what we've got here is
the last iteration again I I I stopped
it at 10 we can go um as as long as we
want again we don't want to overfit but
um now it brought down the error from
4,000 roughly to 400 and this is a
better fit this is what thinks that this
model is and so if I plot this cost we
started at 4,000 in the first iteration
and then it brought it down and down and
down and down up to um and when this
flattens out when this Plateau is done
it it doesn't move anymore that's when
you know that it can't learn anymore
from that data so that the learning is
complete we if if if I plotted this and
it ended up here then I know there's
more learning potentially because I
haven't um plateaued okay so this has
plateaued it learned uh the whole system
and this is what the observed versus
predicted values is if I plot my actual
data and the data I would get from this
model this is what this thing looks like
okay I have one thing to demo before I
let you go I really like this uh
playground from tensorflow um what this
is is a neural network and you can play
with this so this is these are the
inputs there's two inputs there's X1 and
X2 so what are we looking at here we're
looking at this is X1 and X2 right and
what you see is so the there's X1 and X2
and the color is the actual y so this is
a um
classification
uh problem and you're trying to classify
any particular row as blue or orange and
so what you see here in the color is the
actual label or what you're trying to
predict blue or orange and you got two
features which are X1 and X2 and what
you got here is a neural net so this is
the uh layer the input layer and then
you've got two hidden layers which I can
delete or ADD and then you can also add
the number of neurons or delete them
okay so I can add neurons or delete them
and you have got four different
information uh sets of information here
okay so this is the simplest case is
when you've got um two different classes
that you can separate linearly okay so
what is going to happen so um this is
the simplest case so even if this is a
this can be solved by a logistic
regression so I've removed all the
layers this becomes simple logistic
regression and what you see here is
um the the features and again the color
of the dot is the label that we want to
predict and the background is what the
model thinks and so we've succeeded when
the color of the dots um aligns with the
color uh in the background and so you
can see that this even a simple logistic
uh logistic regression can solve this
problem by creating a line there right
now I wanted to show you some things
here so the if I look here these are my
inputs the color is my label or my
output and if I look here what I have is
these are my weights the connection
strength of input um the connection
strength is my weight or parameter so
this is the the parameter and then what
I have here is a set of hyper parameters
this is what's controlling my learning
so this is the EPO this is the iteration
the number of Cycles it goes through
this is the learning rate this is how
fast um of a jump it moves uh between
Epoch and and this can be tuned this is
the activation function this is the um a
mathematical function that again is is
imposed uh on the system and then
there's regularization which is not
applied here and regularization rate and
um and you can change this to regression
you'll see again you can play with it
but I just want to show you a few things
uh but this is really cool to to to play
with so just Google uh tensor flow
playground okay so this is going be
solved this is very simple now if I come
to this problem which is slightly harder
right now this these cannot be divided
by a single line I would need at least
two different lines uh to divide this
and so if I run this with a single
logistic regression it'll never
um it'll never do well because it
doesn't have enough complexity in the
model so this is what we call model bias
uh this model even if it runs for a
million years it'll never solve this
problem and so what I would what I could
do is add a hidden
layer right and if I add um again the
model um architecture really depends on
base knowledge the bigger the model than
the more problems it can solve and um
now that I've done this it seems to be
able to solve this problem right so now
the Orange is under the orange and the
blue is under the blue um and so this
particular
architecture um can solve this model and
again this is a neural network right it
has the input layer the output layer and
two hidden layers okay so now this one
is a little bit more complex um let's
see what it's going to
do oh and that that one solves quite
well so the the blue is under the blue
and the Orange is under the orange and
then you can see the model weight so X1
if I was to write this down this would
be
X1 um time -7 into this minus time -.3
into this and then all of these you'd
have to account for all of these going
through a sigmoid function um so it gets
quite complex mathematically okay and
then we've got this
one this is the hardest one and again
what ends up happening is if it can't
solve it if you add layers and you add
neurons the bigger the model is then it
it becomes really powerful and this is
where these gen models come in and that
they can they can encode a lot of
information and so it's learning and you
can see what's doing every iteration
what is it doing it's making a
prediction calculating an error updating
the weights making a prediction
calculating an error updating the
weights until it finds itself um not
making mistakes anymore
okay and so that that kind of solves the
problem right it's doing a loop of
orange and these are orange and these
are blue maybe this if I put an orange
here it would make an error and then it
would clean that up but at the moment
there is no data there okay and so
that's it um that's all I wanted to show
you um I hope it makes it clearer hello
again so this is ml13 this is
Introduction to generative AI this is I
think the longest lecture here but it
goes into a lot of details on
gen okay so uh what is generative AI uh
so generative AI like we said before is
a subset of machine learning uh
algorithms that generates new uh content
in a lot of um predictive ml the
objective uh the the output of the model
is pretty constrained it it um in
supervised learning it if you're
classifying that it it chooses one of
those uh classes it doesn't go outside
of that um in regression again there's a
a range it's a number uh but so
generative AI um is able to create in
content that it hasn't seen
um but from information that it has seen
before and it emerged in the public eye
in November I think it was 30 November
2022 when open AI launched ch GPT for
free and um before that geni was really
it is a field that has uh been around uh
for a while but um in 2022 it it was
um put in the public eye and the world
has never been the same since um and so
um a lot of what we see G VI um can
create content in different modal so it
could be uh in language it could be text
gener it could be text generation in
language it could be image generation it
could be in videos and audios and so the
inputs and outputs can vary widely but
the most success we've had has been in
in language um a lot of uh the really
cool things are happening in language
and and those are fueled by large
language models llm so tell let me tell
you a little bit more about those so
llms as the name suggest are large
language models um and we'll see what
large means
me and um they are sophisticated tubs
are neural networks right we were just
playing with neural Nets you should know
by now that it's just another formula
it's a
mathematical uh equation that's quite
complex um and we played with the
tensorflow uh playground which uh you
can build your own neural net you can
decide how many uh hidden layers it has
and how many neurons per layer and how
they're connected I don't think you can
change how they're connected I think
it's a feed forward neural net um but
anyway it's just another type of neural
Nets with a particular
uh uh architecture large language models
are characterized by their large number
of parameters they're often in the
billions or trillions um and lmms
understand the probability distribution
of words and sequences if I have time at
the end I'll show you a visualizer of
the Transformer model which is um the
heart of these things and and um
hopefully you'll be able to see what
this means the probability distribution
of words in a sequence um the primary
goal of an nlm is to predict the next
word it's kind of greedy in its um way
of working it it really is a next word
predictor based on uh previous words and
it can capture both the syntax which is
the arrangement of words and the
semantics which is the meaning of words
and LMS have proven useful for a lot of
things including translations and
natural language generation uh speech
tagging information retrieval um there's
a lot of different use cases which we're
going to look into and uh they the way
they work is uh they use self-supervised
learning for pre trainining which
removes the need for explicit labeling
and it's a really cool technique if you
want to look under the hood but this is
out of scope for
me um example tasks uh that llms can
accomplish well we know they can read
okay so they have been super useful in
things like proof reading summarizing
analyzing contact classification we know
they can write so they've been also used
as stylistic polishing agents answering
questions first draft
generation translation code writing and
because they can read and write uh then
they can converse um that's actually not
necessarily true it's not because they
can do these things they've been
fine-tuned to do that uh but they we see
a lot of uh chat Bots a lot of not
natural language um layers on top of uh
knowledge bases and so a lot of common
uses some of the common uses we see is
you know essay writing summarization
translation information retrieval
conversation assistance um image
generators coding tools there's a lot of
there's have been a proliferation of use
cases for um uh
llms okay oops where am I okay so
possible issues with L LMS well
Hallucination is one issue Hallucination
is the uh is when a
model proper information and so it comes
up with a very reasonably sounding
explanation and because the objective
function of an llm is to optimize for
next sequence prediction based on
probabilities it's not optimizing for
accuracy right it it's optimizing for
um sentences that sound reasonable not
sentences that are necessarily accurate
okay so that's the very important thing
to know and so it
sounds like human sentences the actual
content um and accuracy is beyond the
scope of the llm right it it has seen
information and if it sees it enough
then the probabilities would reflect
that but it's not optimization for
accuracy in general okay so that's
called Hallucination is when it comes up
with a response that is that sounds
reasonable but it's not it made it up um
knowledge cut offs um models only see uh
only know about data they've seen up to
a point so if a model was trained in
2024 and you say well who's the
president that was voted in 2025 it does
not know because it did not see that
information uh there's issues with
context windows or or that's at least a
property is how much information can it
take in or spit out um and that varies
widely by models there's issues with
biason toxicity the model sees data from
the internet which of course um there's
a lot of biases um baked into data and
so the model sometimes reflects that um
there's still not really great at
structured or tabular data and they're
not really good at number processing and
we'll see why there's a few issues where
they're not necessarily great at but
they are very powerful and they do a lot
of really cool things and we'll see some
of those things okay so again I'll go
through terminology or or glossery some
of it might seem abstract we're going to
talk a lot about these things in details
but these are things we hear about so
again we talked about artificial
intelligence in one of the lectures it's
techniques that enable computers to
mimic human behavior ml or machine
learning is a subset of that so it is
techniques that allow computers to learn
without explicit programming so they're
making the learning um side of humans
generative AI is a type of AI that
allows computers to generate new content
we've seen all of this now what is an
llm it's a large language model so it's
an umbrella term for model specialized
in
language what is a Transformer so the
Transformer is an algorithm or a neural
network that revolutionaries gen and
underlies LM so it's the heart of the
llm is the actual the
actual um architecture that underly ize
this LNM a prompt is the input to the
model it's the actual text that you're
giving the model that's the input it's
called The Prompt um a token is a word
or part of the world it's the currency
of an llm so the context windows that we
talked about how much it in takes in or
spits out is um it's the unit of
measuring input and output size is a
token an embedding is a numerical
representation of a non-numerical entity
so it's it's a projection into math
medical space and we'll see why this is
important
um rag we hear a lot this is a retrieval
augmented generation this is the use of
an external knowledge base to augment uh
the system again I wanted to put them
all here but we're going to go into more
detail a foundational model is an ml
model trained on vast data sets so that
it could be applied across a wide range
of use cases so this is a very powerful
model that somebody trained uh that you
can use for a wide variety of tasks
so one of the things that people I think
don't really realize is the
size difference between gen models and
predictive ml models and as I said in
some of the previous lectures the bigger
the model the more capable of learning
it is needs more data but there's more
tunable knobs and more information at
Canon code okay and so um I want to just
give you an idea of the generative AI
size uh size so MLS like I said are
sized by the number of parameters this
tells you this is aoxy for how big the
model is and it ranges from one
parameter so we've been playing with
logistic regression uh linear regression
sorry with two parameters ax plus b um
it could be as small as y equals ax
right this is a line that passes through
the the
axis there's no I don't think there's
any real use case for that but you can
imagine that that is the smallest Poss
ible equation and they can go all the
way to two uh terabytes of parameters I
think um if the leaks are correct I
think uh gpts are about 1.8 so I'm I'm
averaging about two trillion
so the predictive ml space is about
millions of parameters right the biggest
ml model that I had ever trained is like
I think a
64,000 uh convolutional neural network
right and so thousands and millions of
parameters in the predictive ml space is
quite powerful um the generative AI
models are in the billions of trillions
of parameters so there's they're roughly
two orders of magnitude uh greater right
and this is the NLP mors law and so
every year model sizes um increased by
roughly 10x so we can see that um uh
Bert and GPT for example Bert is about
340 million parameters here and and this
is this is um you know
2018 um the the gpt3 was at 170 and now
this is 2021 so it's quite out of date
but now we've we've reached the 1.82
trillion parameter
Mark and I want to give you an estimate
of what that means in terms of resources
so a single parameter um in a model or
or a a single number um it when it's in
the computer on the computer it's stored
usually as a 32 FL bit float right and
what that takes is about four four bytes
and so if you've got a billion
parameters just as a paark we we've got
two trillion but let's say you've got a
billion parameters that's roughly about
four gigabytes of RAM just for the
parameters to
load right but when you actually train
the model you need roughly about two 20
times more space because of that whole
go we talked about so you've got your
parameters you're making predictions
you're calculating errors you're
updating parameters and you saving some
metadata and you've got activations
you've got gradients you've got the
optimizer and so there's a lot of U
metadata that is saved across that
process and it takes about 20 times more
space than the parameter size to train
and so if you've got a 1 billion
parameter model uh you need about 80 gb
uh of ram to to actually train this
thing and as you see um we've been we we
were over the 1 billion parameter models
a long time ago these are um reference
this this of course comes from the uh
corser course Andrew Ang's corser course
um if you want to look at that reference
so imagine the requirements of about 1.8
trillion model right so these systems um
are very large and they've put
constraints on compute and data and
they've made parall Iz ation and
optimization both at the hardware level
and a software level a must so there's a
lot of work in the Gen space to optimize
everything from compute to memory to
processing to um loading everything it's
really forced us to really push
optimizations to be able to a better
support these
things so this is um this is a really
cool slide that um I've taken from a
lecture that Yan Dua a
doctoral uh candidate in at Stanford uh
gave this is on YouTube you could see it
in the reference uh section I have a
reference section and um it's uh if you
Google Stanford CS 229 lecture you
should be able to find it but anyway
these are not my estimates these are
yand duas but they're really cool to
give you an estimate of again the
resources required for training and so
he uses the example of uh Lama 3 which
is about 400 billion parameters large
and so it's exactly 405 billion it's
trained on data that's about 15.6
trillion tokens
um the token per parameter ratio is
about 40 tokens per parameter which
means that it is train compute optimal
we didn't talk about this but there is a
paper uh that came
out called the chinella paper which
looked at these are called scaling laws
this
is information about how the performance
relates um performance and model relates
to a model size and and resources it
used in terms of uh various things we
can look at and in the paper I think
their estimate was
that they need you need 20 times the
number of
tokens so if it there should be 20 times
more tokens than parameter size for an
optimally trained model I think and so
This Is 40 tokens so they're they're
higher than that which means that they
um it's train compute optimal and these
are the flops so this is how much um in
a compute it would need uh and so this
is the 6 NP so we would need six times
the size of the data sets times the size
of the model which comes out to this
number here they in the paper they say
that they trained it on
16,000 16,000 gpus that's how many uh
h100 Nvidia gpus uh which have an
average throughput I I fixed the error I
fixed the typo but I left the O uh of
400 Tera flops and so that comes to
about 70 days so if you go in and say
okay well this this is how much compute
I I need and this is how much I have you
divide these two numbers you get about
70 days in the paper they say that you
used about uh 30 million GPU hours which
again comes to pretty close to about 70
days to train this model and so in terms
of cost um he has Young has a lot more
information about estimates he's
estimating that the saty of these people
is about half a million and so on and
and more information but he he comes up
with an estimate that this the the price
tag of this model training is going to
be about is is about 65 to 85
million um and the carbon emitted is
about
440 I guess that's ter Terra
CO2 um which is equivalent to about ,000
return tickets from JFK to London okay
and so
um this shows you that training a model
from scratch which is uh is really
really intense and it's not for the
average uh individual anymore so so it's
now been constrained to companies that
have a lot of resources um you know uh
and they release these models for
General use either as they can allow you
to use it as a as close source as a SAS
solution so they put an API and they
allow you to call that API for cost some
people like meta um they release uh the
open weight model so that means that
they release the weights of the models
and so you can play with it uh and and
deploy it locally but they don't release
um code or information about how it was
trained nor the data set and then
there's open source models which relas
everything so they release the the
weights they release the data was
trained on and the process of which it
was trained so you can reproduce that
process
and usually um academics go for open
source and so they uh release everything
they don't have these budgets I I I was
an academic for a really long time we
don't see these budgets and so work in
Academia interestingly enough um
artificial intelligence or machine
learning is one of those very few cases
where industry has taken over um
academic like it it has superseded
academic research uh because of small
budgets for labs a lot of what academics
do is really focus on algorithms how do
you perfect the algorithm how do you do
smart tricks to uh be able to do some of
these things at at a better cost right
whereas industry there's a lot of money
and so they they crank up the compute um
and so some of the notes is what is the
next model well there's usually a 10x uh
more flop so the the the factor of
increase from cycle to cycle is roughly
10x and um the complexity of this
process of the training process grows
quadratically with the length of the
input sequence so the more data it sees
then the more uh it needs a
quadratic amount of uh resources from
there
okay so again just to compare predictive
ml versus gen um the model sizes are
very different again in the Millions for
predictive ml for genis the millions of
trillions that means that the data
demands are also very different so you
need a lot more data for Gen than you do
for predictive ML and of course that
means that the training compute is a lot
uh bigger and so I was able to train uh
predictive ML on my computer um I don't
think most of us can train uh a gen
model at least not not a serious one um
actually no I should say um uh Andre
karpati who is a part of who is a really
big name in machine learning has written
a nano GPT again you can see this in the
um reference section uh a nanog GPT
which is a smaller model it's about it's
less than 300 lines of so you'll be
able to see what it looks like and you'd
be able to run it and train it um I
think so if you're interested to look at
that and so um in terms of training uh
the way that predictive MLS uses usually
you customize the model with your own
data uh but with geni you it the
training is usually done uh by big
providers and releas to the public uh
for use cases predictive Amal is better
at very specific tasks uh whereas gen is
capable of General tasks in terms of
cost um predictive ml
can be cheap is cheaper so cost divides
into a lot of things right there's the
training cost there's the inference cost
and then there's the total cost of
ownership in terms of training cost gen
definitely costs more in terms of
inference um it should definitely cost
more because it's a bigger model um but
it depends on whether uh you're using a
s solution or you're deploying it
yourself but in general predictive
amount is
cheaper where it becomes cheaper to use
gen is If instead of of training if
there's not a predictive ml model that's
pre-trained and you have to hire people
to train that model and find data and do
all of that and a gen model can already
do that you really save that piece and
so when um a pre-trained predictive ml
model doesn't exist than a gen model can
be cheaper because you're saving on
setting up that model if you
will so the difficulty in predictive ml
like I said is really understanding data
and data processing ml algorithm ml Ops
it's a pretty complex process the
difficulty in gen is really about model
selection um prompt engineering
evaluation because they produce
open-ended results in terms of AWS tools
um predictive ml um the the main service
for that is uh Amazon Sage maker and for
Gen is
bedrock okay so now choosing gen versus
uh predictive ml the main difference
between gen and predictive ml just
there's a lot of differences but the
main three big ones is really the model
training usually for Gen you can't train
the model from scratch just because of
the the estimates that we just saw in
predictive ml it's a lot more um uh it's
easier and so a lot of people do it in
terms of and often you don't there is a
lot of pre-trained models out there but
sometimes for your particular use case
uh you might have to train your own
model the model sizes and the required
resources are just vastly different like
we just saw and gen uh produces
open-ended outputs which makes them a
lot harder to
evaluate we I what I recommend to people
is use gen foundational models for
General tasks uh for quick turnaround so
if you want uh you don't have the time
to get your data to to train the model
to to evaluate it to deploy it to do to
run that whole cycle then um a
foundational model that is ready ready
to go is is a good good option if you
don't have the expertise uh then
something that is pre-done is better but
if you can find a
predictive uh model that's pre-trained
it's going to be cheaper and I'll show
you an
example and uh if you don't have data
then uh Foundation models are a good
idea you use predictive ml for very
specific tasks um tasks that require
great accuracy because um you can
control accuracy and uh compliance a lot
more with predictive ml than than just I
if something is a long-term project the
the the price of a gen model will catch
up to you if it's a really long-term
project training your own model in the
long run uh will become worth it and if
the large the project load is really
large so if if you're pinging that model
millions of times a day then again the
costs will catch up to you and so owning
your own model and having a smaller
model that's customized for you um is
definitely a better idea and if you have
high compliance projects because you
have a lot more control potentially over
a predictive model than a gen
model okay so I'm going to give you an
idea about the trading data um again I'm
going to go through it fairly fast but
it's it's good to see um collecting data
is really hard work um and often it's a
heavily guarded Secret by companies they
don't always tell you what they're doing
and how they're doing it for a variety
of reasons I mean some of it is because
they think of it as the secret sauce for
What from from what the model is
learning um a lot of it also is because
there's compliance and legal issues and
patent laws and it's not really clear
what is being collected and how it's
being used which is very unfortunate but
anyway um we don't always have that
information but here's an example of how
this process would go about you would
download all of the internet uh and so
people use web crawlers uh you can look
at common crawl which indexes the
internet uh there's currently about 250
billion pages online which is roughly
about one p data um
and you extract you extract the text
from the HTML so when you scrape the
Internet it's all HTML docs of course
you extract the actual text from it you
filter undesired content uh you do D
duplicate because of course a lot of uh
pages are found in different places and
several times you add hortic to remove
lowquality documents um there's some
modelbased filtering as well again to to
filter out some stuff
um and then you classify your documents
to be able to
to decide on what how much to use of
what right you don't you definitely want
don't want a model that that's trained
on social media predominantly right so
so understanding what the documents are
and what they relate to and so on um is
important and then you use that uh to
train your model again this is the
devil's in the details and this is a
really high overview I think probably
the the data part the data part of ml is
usually the longest part of ml um and so
so this just gives you an idea of the
steps but this is a long and painful
process there's some open source
academic data sets if you're interested
there's a C4 the pile dolma and fine web
and if you Google those you should be
able to find them uh
online and so again like the the the
bigger the parameter the model is the
more parameters it has and the more data
it needs to see and today's models um
are trained on about 15 trillion tokens
so we saw in the Lama 3 model model it
was about I 15.6 trillion around um so
that's that's where models are today in
the words of yan Lun uh it's trained on
enough data that it would take you and
me 20,000 years to read so these things
chug a lot of data and they have a lot
to learn from and honestly the way they
work um they can do some wonderful some
some really amazing things but again
they they're really big models and they
see a lot of data that you and I can
never process in our lifetime
okay how to choose an llm so um one easy
way to choose of course the to to to
constraint your options is looking at
the input and output uh modalities so uh
different models there's some models
that take input text and and and output
text there's some models that take uh
text to image image to text videos and
so on and so you need to understand what
is going in the model and what is coming
out and that already uh reduces your
pool of models you want to look at the
performance on required tasks so LMS
have a lot of different capabilities
there's um and so there's a lot of
evaluation metrics out there uh that
they're run on and so there's data sets
evaluation data sets that uh look at
reasoning some that look at coding
someone look at summarization and so on
and so if you are interested in a coding
model for example you would want to go
and pick a model that does really well
on coding evaluation
tasks and the way you do that is you um
um look at the model card the model card
is you can think of it as the ID of that
model it's the ID card of that model it
tell you what that model does what's the
input what's the output how it was
trained um how big is it what is it good
at and so on so by looking at the model
cards you would be able to uh
potentially choose one just as a
ballpark for model sizes a model that is
a roughly a billion parameters is good
with pattern matching and basic
knowledge of the world one it gets to
the 10 billion it it has greater World
Knowledge and it can follow
instructions basic instructions but when
the model gets over 100 billion then it
has Rich World Knowledge and complex
reasoning so depending on the task you
want to do um but again I I think very
few no we have 70 billion llama models
so you can depending on what you do the
bigger the model it's true that the
bigger the model the more tasks it can
do but it also means that the more
expensive it is to to to have and and
maintain then there's the close Source
SAS option versus the open source models
model options so SAS models again are
easy to use in application because we're
calling an API they're more powerful
models because these companies have a
lot more money money uh than we do not
true actually with deep seek now um uh
but again close sources is more likely
to um because of the money involved
I am a great proponent of Open Source
because with Collective knowledge um you
know we can get further but again the
the cost of training is not
trivial um in terms of Open Source again
you've got full control of the model you
can run it on your own devices you can
have full control of the data privacy so
you're not sending your data outside of
your domain there's a lot of other
things you can consider but these are
some of the things that I look at
there is a difference between the
predictive ML and the Gen life cycle so
in terms of the predictive ml life cycle
what we do again we looked at this uh we
frame the problem Source the data we
choose the model we train it we test it
we deploy it and we maintain it and we
looked at this a couple of times now in
terms of the Gen life cycle what you do
is um you Scope your project you look at
your business requirements then you
build the system so you choose the model
you prompt engineer um you adapt that
model to your needs that you evaluate
your performance when when you're happy
with it you deploy it and you U monitor
the difference the main difference
really is about this whole sourcing your
own data and
training uh which which is not present
in gen again because of the price tag
maybe one day uh so whereas predictive
ml uh much of the work is about
customizing the model to excel it a
specific task gen is more about
extracting what you need from a general
purpose model so this model knows a lot
of things it knows 20,00
years worth of data 13 15 terabytes uh
trillion tokens 15 trillion tokens and
you're asking it for maybe what a 100
tokens or or a thousand tokens so it's
really like asking for a needle in a Hy
stack and so how you frame that question
or how you talk to the model uh would
kind of helps your success in in getting
what you want and so this is where
prompt engineering comes
in um prompts are again like we said the
input to that model is your question is
what you are telling the model so prompt
engineering is editing that input or or
playing with it to drive the desired
output from the model and if we want to
think of the prompt uh again this is the
input to the model there's a question
there the the most important thing the
most the required thing is the query is
what is it that you want this model to
do is the question but then there's a
lot of other things that you can add to
the context of that prompt and so you
can give it instructions of how to
perform the task you can give it an
objective or a mission to achieve so you
can tell it we are trying to accomplish
X you can give it a Persona you say okay
well you are a doctor or you were a
lawyer this changes the length the
length with which the model gives you
the response you can give it constraints
so you'd say oh avoid this or don't do
that you can give it examples of the
output so you demo the output this is
where zero shot one shot or few shot
learning comes in so you give it an
example and it allows to um uh it it
tries to mimic it context so more
information now you give it tone you can
give it there's a lot more that you can
do but what I want you to know is that
again
this model is huge it's seen a lot of
information you're trying to get a very
specific response out of it and so the
more comp the more well formed your
prompt is that the higher your chances
of success and so prompt engineering
best practices give clear instructions
um structure your prompts include
examples so use all of this that is
available for you right use instructions
um Chain of Thought really helps uh
that's when you tell the model to
explain how it's done something break
down complex Tas prompt um iteration so
you keep uh trying until uh it
works okay um where are we at 34 minutes
okay um enhancing ing llm
performance there's several ways to
enhance llm performance I divided them
in two main categories uh there's weight
preserving techniques this means that
the model itself is unchanged the model
weights are the same but what you do is
you focus on how you interact with that
model so an example is prompt
engineering you are changing how what
input you're giving it but the model
itself is not changed but that does
increase performance rag for example
when you add an external knowledge base
as well that helps the performance of
the LM without changing the itself there
are weight altering techniques so the
model itself changes and so you're
you're fine-tuning you're pre-tuning uh
no you're not pre-training this is from
scratch this is too expensive but you're
fine tuning so you add a layer and
there's there is some there are a lot of
different techniques like PFT um
parameter efficient fine-tuning and
other ways that have been and
quantization and so on that has that
have been optim been made to um
uh make handling models a lot uh better
okay so there's the weight altering
techniques and the weight preserving
techniques the way you should go about
it is uh try the weight preserving
techniques first so do your prompt
engineering then your rag if that
doesn't work then you move on uh don't
start too complex uh because it's going
to get expensive very
fast okay so what is retrieval augmented
generation or rag
um this is a method created by the fair
team at meta to enhance the accuracy of
an llm it improves llms by adding the
information uh by an information
retrieval step before generating an
answer and so what um what we see here
is you've got your user they've got a
prompt this is the question and you've
got a you've got a an external uh
knowledge space here and it could be
anything it could be the documents from
your company it could be um field
specific information and um information
is retrieved from this database it's
used to augment The Prompt um and then
send to the model and that kind of helps
the model in in in different ways and
then you get a response okay so this is
the simplest this is a basic vanilla rag
architecture it's pretty it's pretty
simple uh and so the benefits of rag is
it allows you to potentially site
resources because you've got all of this
metadata here uh data and metadata um
you can add up-to-date information
beyond the cut off date of the model
itself you can add domain specific
knowledge
um of your field you can add specific
knowledge to your company perhaps it
reduces hallucination because it gives
the model more uh resources and it
improves uh performance without actually
training the tradeoffs of course is that
it does increase latency you've added an
extra piece of the system and it it
increases cost so you've added this
extra system right it's cheaper than
actually changing the model but it's not
cheaper than just uh using the The
Prompt engineering for example
this is a more complex view of this so
when you want to set up a rag system
there's a few um steps you can go
through so these are documents you can
chunk them um you chunk them which means
you you you cut them into smaller pieces
or you divide them into smaller pieces
and then you embed them which means you
vectorize them we'll talk a little bit
about what embedding and vectorization
is
um in a little bit uh but you go through
these steps you chunk you embed and then
you store it in the database and then uh
when you want to use the rag uh it's it
you could you query the database uh you
retrieve uh the information you want you
add it to the prompt and then you
generate the answers okay now there's
again this is an abstract representation
of this the devil is in the details
there are so many decisions to be taken
at every step of these how do you chunk
uh what metadata do you save how do you
embed which embedding model um uh uh how
are you going to retrieve are you going
to retrieve based on semantic search or
um what function are you uh looking at
similarity you know there's so many
details across of this but uh my point
in putting the series is to really give
you an abstract view so that it does
it's not as intimidating as um it it
seems okay gen under the hood um
Concepts that are important in llm so
the tokenization token anization is the
initial phase of interacting with LMS
what it involves is the breakdown of
input text into smaller pieces known as
tokens and we'll talk a little bit more
in detail about this so do tokenization
is model dependent each model ships with
its own pre-trained
tokenizer and model
weights and um embeddings are uh in
involve uh transposing the words into
mathematical space and we'll talk a
little bit more about this and the
Transformer is the model at the heart of
LM again we're going to uh have slides
to talk more deeply about these so what
is tokenization again it's the process
of breaking down the text into smaller
units called tokens the benefits of this
is is cost efficiency so the Transformer
performance like we said in the last
structure grows quadratically with um
the terms of the input token so if we
were to tokenize if we use if we could
break words down into letters um that
would make the input a lot longer and so
the informance the performance would be
terrible be really expensive
uh it does reduce tokenization reduces
the space complexity of words so when
you tokenize um then the space is a lot
less so uh instead of having the all of
the conjugation of the words for example
you would have the base word and then
the possible conjugation so instead of
um which reduces the space complexity
you would have less uh information there
it's really good with things uh it's
useful because
then mistakes spelling errors and things
like that are not as uh dramatic to the
model the side effects of course is that
it it creates a lot of weird
behavior um in the model so LMS cannot
spell words because they don't see
letters like we do they see tokens and
so it doesn't understand uh the letter
layer uh they cannot do simple
processing uh string processing again
because they don't see letters they see
tokens uh they are worse at non-english
uh languages because it's it's not the
same the the tokenization is optimized
on the English language and so other
languages might not work as well it's
very bad at simple arithmetic because
instead of the tokenizer cuts
um numbers at different rates it's not
it doesn't see it as the base 10 system
that we do um and then it has trouble
coding in Python again because of the
tokenization of all of the spacing uh
which some of these have been fixed in
in various models but some of the the
reasons for the these is really
tokenization and different again like I
said different tokenizers different
models come with different tokenizers
and this this website can show you what
the tokens look like for different uh
for different models and so you can play
with that this is an example of hello
there it's a it's it's nice to meet you
for the tokenizer for Google uh Gemma
and GPT 4 oh and you can see here that
uh the apostrophe s is is treated
differently this is this is such a small
sentence but uh you could see that there
is a
difference okay word in vetting or
vectorization um so machine learning
models are just large statistical
calculators uh they work with numbers
not with words right we as humans um
communicate with words but models and
math works with numbers and so we have
to convert the words into numbers and
this is what's called embedding or
vectorization so Vector embedding
vectorization embedding is are all the
same things it's really a projection of
text or image is or whatever your input
data is into mathematical space which
means
numbers and so again this is a numerical
representation of non-numeric entities
and there's different examples of how we
did this across ages and so one hot
encoding for example if you have an
example that that that's one way to
vectorize uh a discrete class uh tfidf
which is term frequency inverse document
frequency was one way we did it before
word toac is really cool um here's the
paper so his historically some examples
are in the 1954 there was what they
called bag of Words which is a simple
approach what it means is they just
counted words in a document so um the
more a if the were if there was more
Sports words than anything else then
they would categorize this was made use
for classification they would classify
it as a
sports um document for example but that
was the simplest way is how do you take
words and get numbers out of them and
counting in the 1954 was the easiest way
and so this was where bag of words come
in in 1972 it became a little bit more
sophisticated where tfidf means the term
frequency inverse document frequency so
you counted but then you divided by how
often that um term appears in the
document so it's it's a frequency count
now it's not a a base count or an
absolute count it's it's a
frequency and then um in
2013 Google released the word Toc which
was really really cool and I think is
underlying a lot of the advancement in
LP that we see today um what this is is
is um High dimensional vectors
encapsulating semantic
associations and again this was this I
think is is one of the flag moments this
is a pivotal moment um advancement in in
NLP and what it really showed is so what
they did is they took this model
embedding model they gave it um a lot of
Text data and they trained it
and it came up with these Vector
embeddings uh Vector representations in
in high-dimensional space but then what
they showed is that you can do math with
words and so if you said something like
King minus man plus woman the model
would give you Queen and so this
transformed
NLP uh and modeling on text because now
uh we understand that we can do that
projection really well and and that's
the paper and you can read a little bit
more about
it um um the Transformer this is the
last uh big component I wanted to talk
about the Transformer is really the
architecture that the the model
architecture that is at the heart of the
llm um it's the heart of many llms it's
a neural network again we played with
neural network so if you're not a
familiar go back to the previous
lectures um and it was introduced in a
paper uh which was called attention of
all you need in 2017 this was work from
uh researchers from Google and the
University of Toronto it was initially
designed for sequence to sequence um
tasks like translation it was I don't
know that they knew that it would um
take the World by storm this is what it
looks like so again because um these
things the the mathematical model tends
to be too complex we we visualize them
um abstractly like this so this is you
got your inputs uh
we I don't want to go into too much
detail but you've got an encoder and
then you've got a decoder and then
there's a cross attention in between uh
there's a really good um lecture on
YouTube again in the reference about how
this all works and and you can build it
from scratch if you want so look at the
the references but
um what a lot of people in the field did
this this started as a translation paper
and then what in 2017 and then what
people did after that is they copy
pasted the
architecture um and change the input so
they changed the the ve the
embedding uh the vectorization yeah the
embedding and it does wonders I mean
it's it's still at the heart of a lot of
things we do there has been some changes
to the architecture very minor from the
paper uh but again you can take a look
the main before that uh the way we did
sequences is was through uh rnn's
recurrent neural networks and their
different variations uh but those uh
dealt with data qually which meant you
couldn't paralyze them and um so rnn's
um you know you can look into them but
the the differences that made the
Transformer the next leap is because it
was
parallelizable and so we can train this
on distributed compute and it can get a
lot larger um there's they introduced
something called positional encodings
where it doesn't need to retain the
sequence anymore it it retains a vector
of where every word is and and that
helps it not retain sequence and it
helps again in paral ation and they
introduce something called attention
heads which allows the model to assign
different weights to different words
depending on their context um there is
this I wanted to show you I think this
is my last slide yeah okay so there's I
wanted to show you this this is a really
cool website again you can see it um
this is based on the nanog
GPT
um and what this shows you is this is
the embedding this is the input okay so
you've got your data this is the words
and this is the embedding Vector right
so you've got your your
tokens uh there's
tokenization
and data visualization empowers users so
you can see here that empowers has been
split into two different tokens so
already this is tokenized you can see
and this is the positional uh encoding
so this is the position of each word and
then it's been vectorized so this is the
edting the vectorized so this word has
been um changed into this vector and
this is using a vector representation
that is
768 numbers long the vectorization
changes from company to company and from
provider to provider Google uses a
vector that's
67,68
768 um in length I think gpts are closer
to the 3,000 Mark the more numbers uh
you have in that Vector then the more
dimensionality you are um Gathering and
so there's there's more information that
you can potentially so just keep that in
mind so this is 6
768 it's late here
um and so now what you see here is this
is the information and it goes through
the the layers the this is distributed
so these are different processes
happening um and then you can see here
there's a tension so it's giving
different words different
um uh evaluations or importance and it
goes through the layers and uh what ends
up happening with what I want to show
you is right here it takes the the
tokens and then it uh creates a
probability distribution so this is the
probability distribution and so it says
data visualization empowers the users to
make and it's a next remember it's a
next word predictor in the sequence and
so this is the possible words that could
be next and it thinks that um the next
word based on the prob ability
28.3 is visualized so data visualization
empowers users to make uh visualize now
again this is not a great model and that
it's the nanog GPT it's a small model
it's not been trained on a lot of data
but it gives you an example of this how
this whole thing works now temperature I
didn't talk about temperature and top
key and top K these are um these are
hyper parameters that you can or um just
variables that you can change that um
change the Model Behavior and what these
do is they change the randomness in the
model and so if the temperature is zero
what you can see here it's doing is it's
changing the probability distribution at
the output layer and so if this is zero
this model becomes deterministic it
gives the highest the word the top word
the highest amount and so it'll
repeatedly do that if you ask it over
and over if you make this um highest
then you can see it changes the
distribution there's a lot more
Randomness now the probabilities are
very close to each other and so it will
choose one at random different times so
these are what the top P top K
temperature though they they really play
at the level of the
probabilities okay so that is it for me
these are my references um yanda's
lecture is really good it goes into what
llms are and it is more technical it is
a Stanford lecture in CS so it goes a
little bit more into the weeds if that's
what you want but I I personally enjoyed
it um there's some lectures here from
Andre on he does a lot about how do you
build a GPT how do you build a tokenizer
how do you do all of these things really
cool if you're interested in the depth
uh I personally really like Andre and I
follow him uh and I take a lot of his
cero courses in DB so these are there
for you and that is it hello again um so
this is the four the final uh lecture in
this miniseries so this is ml104
architecting Gen
systems and um so this is a a reminder
that um the tech and ml um serve the
business right so um it has to be linked
to the use case it has to be the proper
tool for the use case so the first
question is to ask is is AIML the right
tool for the job
and whether it's ml AI analytics Tech
they're all tools to solve
problems but you have to choose the
right tool um ML and AI are pretty
powerful uh but not nothing not well if
you have a hammer I guess everything
looks like a nail but ideally you would
choose the finest Tool uh for your job
so any repeating task in a system is
worth automating um if that task is
deterministic you know the rule you know
the the the the system uh formula like
we just saw in the previous lecture then
you can automate that with um with a
software system with devops with a rule
based systems um if however the task
involves miss or reasoning or a pattern
you don't understand then that's where
ml uh comes in and again anytime you
have data then ml is an option like I
said in the previous lecture but it
really shines when there is um change
when there's scale and when there's
complexity
okay but um again you just have to look
at what your use case is what are your
possible options and if ml is your best
option now now that you've chosen AI or
ml you have to choose whether is
predictive ml or gen and we went a
little bit over last lecture about when
to choose either um this is a
reiteration but um here what I want to
show is
that um both in predictive ML and geni
uh you can have custom models that are
trained to on your own data um or SAS
solution so this is a pre-trained model
um and it could be a pre-train model
that you deploy yourself or it could be
a a pre-trained model that is um hosted
by a provider for you either case I
didn't put an extra line here for that
but um like we saw in the last lecture
custom models in the Gen space are very
very costly so that's unlikely to happen
um and predicted ml um Solutions in
general um there are pre-trained models
out there but the majority of cases are
usually Uh custom built and so uh we
said this before but the main differen
is to keep in mind is that uh the model
size is very very different um uh the
training there is a lot more work in
training and data Gathering so on
predictive ml than in gen and that gen
gives open-ended results
right and so the predictive the the
cases that we see normally so again this
this Matrix you can have predictive ml
that is custom or that ones that are
pre-trained or the ones that provide are
provided uh by a third entity and in gen
you can have all three as well but the
pattern that we see Mo most in the wild
is that um gen people use a third party
option um an API call um and in the
predictive ml space it's usually custom
model so when I'm talking of going to um
compare these two again it's I
understand it's not Apples to Apples
it's it's but these are the patterns
that we see more often and again when I
say cost there's um it's a proxy there
is uh training cost there's inference
cost and there's total cost of ownership
and of course there's the cost of having
personnel and training personnel and
collecting data and so on um but on
average um gen 10 to be more
expensive and so this is a again we've
seen some elements of this uh the model
size is a lot bigger uh the initial
training investment is a lot bigger in
predictive ml I think this should be
clear by by now uh you have to collect
your data you have to train you have to
have the skill set so the data
availability is required here whereas
it's not in in gen the expertise is
required whereas it's not in gen not as
much anyway um so the initial investment
uh required for predictive Mount is a
lot higher than it is for J so if you
have a use case where you really want to
hit the ground running uh and and prove
value really fast then gen might be a
better option for you um in terms of
inference cost um again it's not Apples
to Apples but on average gen tends to be
more expensive because these models are
bigger because they're more expensive to
host because that model provider needs
to get um their their service paid for
um in terms of model control oops in
terms of model control uh you have a lot
more model over a custom a model that is
in that that is customed to you that is
yours as opposed to a model that is
hosted by somebody else in terms of
deterministic or not um predictive
models are a lot more deterministic
foundational models um or llms uh tend
to be a lot more uh
probabilistic and less deterministic and
so depending on if you have a and I said
this before in the lecture so this is a
repeat if we you have a project that is
really long term it's it's it's a long
project um that it makes sense to use
predictive ml because the cost of gen is
going to catch up with you uh again if
your work size uh workload size is
really large again the cost will catch
up with you so a predictive model might
be a better option and if you have high
compliance than a a predictive ml custom
predictive ml model is a probably a
better choice uh you control a lot more
uh than you do with a foundational model
um so now this this is here we we're
we're comparing Apples to Apples and
that here we're looking at a predictive
ml SAS solution uh versus a gen SAS
solution so this is document processing
uh textt trct is an AWS Service uh that
is a model as a surface it's a
pre-trained model um and um I'm looking
at what it would cost to process about a
million Pages a month uh with the um
with the assumption that there's about
676 words per
page and um if I do that on text track
that gives me about 1,500 USD a month uh
if I do that on Nova bedro through Nova
um it'll cost me about 2,600 which is a
2X roughly if I do it on clots on it
it'll cost me 11,000 right and
so novas are I'm they're surprisingly
cheap I think that's one of their um
uh good features is that they're fairly
cheap uh but the idea is that if you
have a predictive ml model that is
pre-trained and does a specific task
that you want it to do that model I'm
again different environments and
different things might vary but I am
willing to make the bed that uh it'll be
cheaper than a gen model simply because
of the size and the resources required
to host a
model okay so we're going to talk talk a
little bit about um so let's say you've
decided that um ml is a great fit for
their use case and uh within uh AIML
you've decided that gen is um a better
fit for your use case so let's say you
need to show your stakeholders um really
fast value and so you don't have really
a lot of time to to think about custom
models there isn't a SAS there isn't a
pre-t trade model that does exactly what
you want it to do but an llm does it for
you so that's that's um you've decided
that uh hypothetically that J is the
thing for you let's architect a
system and so um what I'm going to show
you here is a series of conceptual
diagrams um so they they
abstract uh the main building blocks in
a system and how they are
connected there are many different tools
that can fit into these blocks so when I
say a rag system there's many different
ways there's a million ways to ro
there's a million ways to build that
system in technical terms but um it
serves the same function and so uh I'm
trying to help you abstract all of the
important uh building blocks and so the
main point of this exercise is really to
get a high level view of the system um
and it's very important to understand
what the function of that uh service is
or that piece that component what the
pros and cons of having it are and um
and then once you get that and you
decide that that component is important
to the system you can go in and dig into
the technical implementations what tools
fit into that uh or serve that function
and how you would Implement that that
that is beyond the scope of this
particular call I'm just looking at
conceptual uh big component diagrams but
uh I think within uh if you're taking
the um gen free boot camp then you're
going to have some opportunities to do
that work okay
so um J architecture Ground Zero is a
model call by the way uh these series
are uh not exactly but they are based on
uh the book AI engineering by uh chip
hen uh I really enjoyed that book I I I
like both her books actually so um it's
a really good resource the first book uh
which is designing machine learning
systems that talks more about predictive
ML and this one um gen AI engineering
talks about generative AI
um okay so at the heart of a gen system
is a um geni model we're going to call
it a generation model or and um so let's
say we're using text here so it's going
to
llm and the way this system works is
you've got a model here um the user
sends in a query again we call this a
prompt and then uh gets a response which
in the field is called a completion okay
uh gets a response which is a completion
and already um this is a very very
powerful system in that these models can
do a lot of things so they can they can
summarize text they can classify text
they can an they can answer questions
they can write drafts for you they can
write code for you there's a lot of
things that these things uh can do
they're pretty um impressive
actually um it is important to note that
if you are using a um
a foundational model by a third party
provider you're not hosting it yourself
that this um here I should have put a
line here this is within the uh domain
of the model provider so the data is
going outside of your own uh
jurisdiction okay so this is at the
heart of the system this is the biggest
piece is the model call now um like I
said in previous lectures these models
are very big they have a lot of encoded
information and what you're looking for
is a particular answer or some sort of
uh query that you're looking at or
information um and really it's like
looking at for a needle in a Hast stack
and so what you want to do is you want
to um give that model more information
and more
context uh for it to be able to help you
the best way and so that's where the
anatomy of a prompt comes in so uh I'm
not going to go through this in detail
because we already in previous lecture
if you've missed it please go back uh
but the idea is that a prompt of course
is the input like I said prompt
engineering is the the process of uh
editing the input or formulating the
input or formatting it to drive the
desired output and um The Prompt itself
uh as at the heart of it is a question a
query what it is that you want the task
what task do you want the model to do
but that's not all of it you can add so
many things to a prompt and so you can
add instructions um um this is steps to
perform you can add objectives so you
can tell it um something you want to
achieve the goal you want to achieve you
can give it a Persona so you you tell it
oh this in terms of context you are a
doctor you are a lawyer and that gives
you different
viewpoints um you can give it
constraints you can say avoid this or or
or don't do that you can give it
examples so you can give it an a Dem a
demo of the output so this is where a
zero shot one shot and few shot learning
come in or you can give it more context
for relevant information or you can
change the tone and there's more this is
just an example but the idea is that you
can change the prompt you can enrich The
Prompt uh for the model to be able to to
help you better so you can give it more
instructions and so this is what we've
added here we've added this where you
are adding the context construction so
this this prompt here that we're
building you're building it a little
with with um with a little bit more uh
awareness right and so that comes here
so as I move through these diagrams the
new piece that I'm building in is in
Orange and the rest is in Black just to
allow you to to follow through so we
enhance the context or the prompt or the
model input and so this becomes um a
little bit more information for the
model
right the other thing we can do is to
add external an external knowledge base
this is a rag system so you've got a
database here and then the input
retrieved from that database goes into
the prompt uh construction and then it's
given to the model model there's a lot
of reasons why you would want to add rag
again we talked about rag in the last
lecture so you can go back and see
that now if you want you can add uh
guard
rails uh for your model so as again like
I said in the beginning if you are using
a uh SAS solution from a model provider
then again this piece right here or or
this here this this generation call um
that is not in your domain that goes to
the provider and so there's information
here crossing your your your your your
company Network and so what you can do
here is you can put input guard rails
what that does is it validates that the
input going out of your organization is
um based on your Norms it's compliant
with your Norms is there any pii in
there do I mask anything is is any
information sensitive information that I
don't want out of my company and so that
where that's where inut guards in uh
before they before they leave your um
Network and then you can add output
output guard rails because uh open um
because LMS give open-ended mod uh
inputs
outputs you can um put output guard
rails to check whether there's any
whether again the response is compliant
with your um requirements is is there
any safety contraints is there any bias
is there any um is there any uh
profanities all of that stuff that you
wouldn't want uh your user to get you
can put a a catch uh right
here and so now we've augmented the
system again with these uh guard
rails what we could also do for example
is ADD routers and gateways and so what
this um does is that this model
generation you can this generation piece
here is uh a model it goes out to this
is a model call and what happens is that
um different models have different
strengths so some models are better at
reasoning some models are better at
coding some models are better at
summarizing and so on and if you have
users that um if you're supporting all
sorts of requests you might want to do
different model calls based on the user
input and so what you would do is you
you write this class uh a wrapper class
with which is we're calling here a model
Gateway which uh routes uh different
calls to different models depending on
certain criteria right what this does is
it abstracts the model
use um from the underlying model it just
puts an abstraction layer which allows
you to switch models
seamlessly okay now again one added uh
something else we can add as well as uh
caches caches in different parts of your
system system can reduce latency but
they also can reduce cost because you're
not hitting your databases or you're not
hitting that model as um as often oops
that's the and so you can add caches uh
at the query level you can add them at
the the knowledge base level you can add
them in different places and again you
can there's all sorts of questions about
what types of caches and how do we cash
and when do you know that in all of
these different scenarios uh there's all
sorts of uh uh detailed questions that
can follow but I'm just showing you uh
an abstract uh
system and uh
so you can also add functionality with
agents so you can add agents that that
that do various things
um and then you can add all sorts of uh
interesting it is a software system at
the end of the day right you you would
want to follow best practices you add
Authentication authoriz ation State and
session management monitoring and
observability pipeline orchestration
human feedback there's so many other
things that you can to make this model
this system production ready but what I
wanted to show you is if had I shown you
this I hope this is now understandable
or or seemingly digestible but had I
shown you this uh from the very
beginning it could have potentially um
looked
intimidating um what I want to encourage
you is to really look at everything you
look at online all the different
diagrams from this lens from the
conceptual lens and try to understand
what the component is which bucket does
it fit into what does it do um and then
not to really get down bogged down with
the technology the technology changes
really fast um and it's it's moving
super fast but what you really need to
have is an overview of the system and
the
components okay and that is it I hope
this series was useful full um if you
have any questions let me know I am
going to release the the
the the slides with the uh Jupiter
notebooks I think that's it yeah that's
si in the Jupiter notebooks hope this
was useful