after reading tons of productivity books
I came across so many rules like the
2-year rule the 5 minute rule the 5c
rule no not that 5-second rule the
problem is that these rules were meant
for companies or entrepreneurs but I was
able to adapt them to my studies during
med school and drastically cut down in
my procrastination so I'm going to share
with you two different two-minute rules
for the next 2 minutes the first 2
minute rule comes from getting things
done by David Allen he says if it takes
2 minutes to do get it done right now
for example if I need to take out the
trash today it takes 2 minutes to do so
if I'm thinking about it now might as
well just do it now instead of writing
it down on a to-do list or probably
forgetting about it or having to come
back to it later which takes more than 2
minutes that's how I see it so here's a
list of things that might take 2 minutes
throughout the day like organizing your
desk or Watering your plants or clipping
those nasty Nails I just do it when I
notice it but these little things start
to add up so this rule biases my brain
towards taking action and away from
procrastination the second two-minute
rule comes from Atomic Habits by James
Clear he says when you're trying to do
something you don't really want to do
simplify the test down to 2 minutes or
less so doing your entire reading
assignment becomes just reading one
paragraph or memorizing the entire
periodic table becomes memorizing just
10 flash cards now some of you might
think yeah this is just a Jedi mind
trick like why would I fall for it how
is this at all sustainable and to that
he says when you're starting out limit
yourself to only only 2 minutes so back
in med school I wanted to build a habit
of studying for 1 hour every day before
dinner so I tried this trick but I
limited myself to Just 2 minutes I'd sit
down open my laptop study for 2 minutes
and then Clos my laptop and went to do
something else it seems unproductive at
first right it seems stupid but staying
consistent with this two-minute routine
day after day meant that I was becoming
the type of person who studies daily I
was mastering the habit of just showing
up because a habit needs to be
established before it can be expanded
upon if I can't become a person who
studies for Just 2 minutes a day I'd
never be able to become the person that
studies for an hour a day you got to
start somewhere but starting small is
easier there's a lot of other useful
tips from books I cover more here in
this video on three books in 3 minutes
check it out and if you guys like these
types of videos let me know in the
comments below I'll see you there bye